Hello everybody. My name is Harris. I'm
a research scientist in yearblogs. Um so
I will be giving the the rest of the uh
presentations. They will be shorter than
session one. And be before I start with
the second presentation today. I'd like
to go through the the course structure
using the course website. I hope that
you all have access to this. This is the
the main course website just in in dark
mode. Um so if you scroll down you will
see all the course units here uh along
with the getting started page. So first
things first so in the getting started
um I hope that you have all followed the
instructions on first install in
installing Julia and then installing
your blocks and also all the
dependencies that we're going to need
for the tutorials and by dependencies I
mean Julia packages other than your
blocks that we will be using in our
tutorials. So this is what this block of
code uh is doing. Uh it's going to
download a file with all the
dependencies and it will essentially
create a new Julia environment with all
those dependencies installed along with
neuroblocks.
Um so if you have done this if you have
followed these steps before today or
before this afternoon can I please ask
you to to run them again because you
made some recent changes to neuroblocks
and to our dependencies. So essentially
by that I mean if you if you have a
folder that looks like this oops sorry
this is too
small.
Um yeah if you have a folder that looks
like this uh when uh after you run that
block of code you're going to have the
manifest file and a project file. So the
project file is is downloaded and the
manifest manifest file is generated from
the project. Um, so and never mind if
your notebooks are actually here in the
same same directory. They could be here.
They could be in a separate folder.
That's fine. But, uh, what I want you to
do is again if you have done run these
steps before today, before this
afternoon, just delete these two files,
the manifest and the project to
um, uh, come back here in the terminal.
Sorry, open a Julia session in that same
folder and run these uh, these lines
again. So that way you will download the
new dependencies and the new versions of
them and you'll have the most recent new
blocks and the most recent
dependencies. And uh for the Jupyter
notebooks, yeah, it's just to be safe.
I'm not sure when when you downloaded uh
them from the Google Drive link here,
but just to be safe, you can download
them again. Um but they should be stable
from now on. If not, I will let you
know. And again the note it doesn't
matter if the notebooks are in the in
here or they're in a separate folder
within that environment. This doesn't
matter what the only thing that it
matters is uh you will run this command
um on the directory where the project
tumble and the manifest tombble files
are
uh every time that you run a notebook
basically. So, but of course after the
presentation we're going to have plenty
of time for, you know, exercises going
through notebooks and if you have any
issues with the the installation, we can
help you. Uh
then so going back to the homepage
um as I said the the the sessions from
now on will mostly be practical. I will
be giving you maybe a 10 or 15 minutes
presentation which will be a conceptual
introduction to the topic of that
session and the rest of the time is
working on notebooks with you know text
and code blocks uh on the the theme of
the day or the of the session and uh
these are the themes basically split
into units. We will start uh this
session with introduction to
Julia. Uh and then tomorrow on the
morning session we will do the
differential equations in Julia and
plotting with Mikey. Uh Mike is just a
plotting ecosystem in Julia. So we'll do
this together on the first session
tomorrow and on the second session
tomorrow we will look into uh
essentially neuroblocks core how uh the
blocks components and the connections
between them how they are structured in
your blocks and how you you can create
your own both blocks and uh connection
rules for
blocks. Um so moving on on Wednesday the
first session we will look into
essentially the the core components of
any computer science model. uh which
could be uh neurons, neuronal masses and
external
sources and then we will combine these
uh with you know different combinations
to create circuit models. That's session
two of Wednesday and in fact this
session this is the bread and butter of
neurblocks. So this session will include
two separate uh models from the
literature. one model that Lily went
through the cortical stridal model of
category learning we will see a subset
of that circuit and another model um
that has already been published from
other group um and moving on to Thursday
we will look into decision- making and
reinforcement learning uh that's session
one and session two respectively
decision making will go through a
popular model from the literature that
is trying to approximate the you know
the behavioral results that we see with
perceptual decision making and is uh
exhibiting behavior similar to a drift
diffusion model that cognitive
scientists use uh but this time in a
circuit and the synatic plasticity
reinforcement learning. Uh here we will
see both synaptic plasticity in a in a
cortical model just letting it simulate
and seeing how the connections adapt
over time and also reinforcement
learning in a category learning task
where we will build uh again a subset of
the big cordal model that Lily presented
and we will let it learn over iterations
by giving it images and giving it um
feedback about the category that those
images belong in. And finally for the s
first session of uh Friday we're going
to look into dynamic coal modeling and
specifically spectral uh DCM
um and we will fit um models to to
simulated data. We're using that and for
the second session of Friday which is
the last session of the course we left
it open uh because every other session
includes both exercises that are more
straightforward. the the exercises have
to do with you changing something in the
code and noticing some result but also
each session includes challenge
problems. So these are sometimes
open-ended problems uh but definitely
more involved uh in every case. So after
you go through the material of a day
let's let's pick let's pick a session
the neurons neural math and sources
after you go through this material which
by the way this exact material on the
website is the same as you will see in
the notebook. So when you when you open
uh this notebook here, you will see
exactly the same thing in a slightly
different format. So after you you go
through the material and any exercises
within it, at the end we have the
challenge problems and and these are
just recommendations that we give you
like some for future directions to work
on based on what you have just learned.
Um so yeah after you finish with the
previous steps the having gone through
the the notebook material you can pick
any one of these and work on that for
the remainder of the session. So for
Friday the on the second session we left
it open as a you know uh as a session
where you can come in and work on any of
these challenge problems that you have
started on previous days but have not
finished or if you want to look at the
some of the material that's already
there again and ask us any questions or
work on any problem that you that you
like even your own problems you can come
in and start modeling your own circuits.
So that's the last session on Friday.
Um so I think yeah this is all the the
housekeeping that I want to to
do. Um and as I said yeah I will keep it
short with the the the presentations
every session so you'll have more time
to do uh actual coding. So and the first
uh presentation is actually
complementaryary to helmet's
presentation. Helmet talked to you about
why we chose Julia for nearblocks. I'd
like to do a more general introduction
to Julia as a language
uh because that this is going to be
helpful when you work with neuroblocks
through the code interface but also for
some steps of the GUI to understand
Julia better will help you even in the
GUI
um right so what is Julia so Julia
development started right here at MIT at
uh that was the very early days and
version 1.0 show got released uh almost
uh 10 years later in August of
2018. Um and Jul has been growing
basically throughout that time and from
the 2018 onwards and we'll see some
numbers on that. So Zlay is a is a
dynamic interactive language. Um it's
intuitive and it's expressive. Uh where
you can easily write you know high level
syntax and essentially by high level
syntax I mean anything that is not close
to you know machine code um as for
instance C is uh and it's it's built
upon types and multiple disputes. So
we'll do we'll talk a lot about types
and multiple disputes. It's two very
core concepts of Julia and one way of
think of that of this design is an
alternative to the object-oriented
programming design that for instance uh
Python has uh you will see more of this
in both today in the tutorial but also
tomorrow and uh yeah helmet also
mentioned this phrase which Julia works
like Python and runs like C. It's
essentially this phrase sums up all the
previous points and by that we mean that
you know it's uh it's an expressive
language. It's easy to write but also
you can make it very performant with a
few extra steps uh if you take them and
also just to get this out of the way on
the first slide. Julia is one based
indexing. Uh if you're coming from
Python, yeah, there might be some
shortcomings. Uh I find hard sometimes
to switch between the two, but basically
indexing in Julia begins from one. And
by this I mean in any collection of
elements, the first element is index
one. Uh in Julia, similar to
MATLAB, right? Um so I'd like to go
through all these all these points, all
these features of Julia that I mentioned
one by one. And first what I mean about
about Zula being dynamic and interactive
is that Julia is a is a compiling
language but uh you can u very easily
work on it in a dynamic environment
where you know you write lines of code
you evaluate those lines of code and you
move on to the next one um similar to to
Python and
MATLAB and here are three interfaces
where you can do that first one is the
the ripple the the ripple uh stands for
read evaluate print loop It's yeah, it's
exactly what it says on the tin. You
write your code line by line by line.
The Jula compiler reads that code and
evaluates it and it gives you a result
immediately on the next line.
Um, this is easy to do if especially if
you're prototyping or if you if you want
to check something very quickly, maybe
uh harder to develop, you know, longer
pieces of code just in the ripple. But
then you can move on to something like
uh VS Code. VS code has an extension
which I think works uh great. So there
you can see an example that
uh that you know as a person is typing a
command you have the autofill of you
know uh Julia functions that start with
ma for instance map and then next to
that you also see a panel that gives you
the dock string of map that is you know
the that that is fetched from Julius
documentation so it tells you exactly
what map is doing as you type and also
it's it's very handy to for plotting
because it's time that you that you plot
something on with your code. Then uh a
second panel will open here and you will
see that plot there and you can even
flip between the history of plots in
your current
session. Um so so it has this uh history
component and also uh there is a there
is a ripple open on the bottom that this
ripple on the bottom part is exactly the
same as that ripple. So you can even
type commands directly there or you can
evaluate your commands from up from from
the script that you have um there and
you can evaluate them one by one or you
can run the the entire script and then
you're just going to get the you know
the final result printed. Uh and a third
option which is actually the the main
the main one that we're going to use for
this course is uh Jupyter notebooks. Uh
you might be familiar with Jupyter
notebooks from Python. This is exactly
the same uh structure. Essentially,
Jupyter itself supports both uh Julian,
Python and
R2. Um and uh in a Jupyter notebook,
it's um it's a handy interface
especially if you have lengthy pieces of
text that are longer that you know
single line comments. So, as you can see
there, we can have um any text have can
have text blocks and code blocks
interspersed in in one notebook. And uh
this is exactly what every every page on
our website looks like. And this exactly
the same in the notebooks when you open
them. So I would recommend everybody
using those notebooks that we have. But
of course you're not limited to them. So
for instance, if you have VS Code
already installed, uh it's one extra
step to install the dual the dual
extension in VS Code and you can just
copy paste the code from the website to
to VS Code and start evaluating it there
and start running it there. That's
completely up to you and we can help you
if you want to set that up. But the dude
with the notebooks are there and they're
already
ready. Now the second claim that I made
is that Zlay is intuitive and
expressive. Uh and here I'm just showing
you an example that is very much
relevant to ours. This is a function
that u uh ident finds a spike and uh
keeps the time for that spike as it
integrates a model and u we can see the
expressiveness here because uh it's as
you can see on top there is this using
unitful line where basically unitful is
a package that comes from with actual
physical units right so we can easily um
uh import this package and pick three
units I want to import from that package
and use those units immediately in our
code almost the same as we would in
paper, right? You can see that you know
R is equal to 100 megahons. Uh that's
standard Julia syntax uh that you know
that the Julia compiler can read and a
human can read very easily. Um and even
within the loop sorry within the the
first spike function we have this extra
expressiveness because we're not limited
by you know some some rules that other
languages impose. For instance, in
MATLAB and Python, um even in R as well,
the the the documentation, the official
documentation will make the claim that
try to use vectorzed code because that
this is faster, right? So if you wrap
everything, if you organize your data
into matrices and vectors and doing
operations with with linear algebra,
basically that that's going to be faster
than looping over element by element. In
Julia, that's not the case. you can you
can use vectorzed operations or you can
use loops and the the performance will
be uh almost the same. So you have this
extra expression as you know like uh
it's it depends from person to person of
course but I would I would make the
claim that it's easier to read out a
loop versus reading uh a matrix
multiplication and figuring out exactly
what's
happening. But also the fact that Julie
is um is expressive uh comes from the
fact that it allows you to to build uh
to essentially design your own syntax on
top of the language the language syntax
that is already there and that is uh
through macros. Uh so macros help you
you know make those you know domain
specific languages within Julia. For
instance, uh on the bottom left you can
see differential equations where you can
uh type in a system of differential
equations symbolically, right? That
comes from modeling toolkit that helmet
mentioned as well. So u Julie is able to
parse those symbols and the it
eventually creates this differential
equation system uh because of these
macros that you can see the add
variables and add parameters for
instance and add equations. Those things
tell the Julia compiler that you know
now you're gonna see a block of symbolic
code uh with maybe you know some symbols
and some uh default values or some some
equations split by the tilda symbol. Um
so this extends the the language
capabilities a lot. And similarly in the
if you want to for instance solve some
optimization problem you can use jump
and in jump you can use a similar very
high level syntax of you know first you
you start with a model and in your model
you pick your optimizer and then you you
just iteratively add stuff to your
model. For instance you add a variable x
and x is strictly positive is sorry not
negative in this case. Uh you add a y
that is bounded uh both uh from both
ends. You add an objective function. You
add some constraint and at the end you
can print the model and you have this
nice symbolic print of your model. And
if I were to to show you one more line
then you can actually solve this model
using the optimizer that you pick and it
gives you the you know whatever
minimizes your objective function. But
also of course and this is the reason
why we're here neuroblocks you know
share this shares this value. It's very
easy in neurob blocks as you can see
there in that small block of code to
just define the two neurons. In that
case we have an excitatory husking
hackling neuron and an inhibitory
haskkin hackling neuron and then we
create an empty graph because every
model every model in neur block starts
as a graph and we connect the inhibitor
neuron to the excitatory one. So this
simple model with two neurons connected
one way uh can be defined in uh these
few lines of code.
Now the next thing uh as I said types in
multiple dispatch they are the uh at the
Julia at Julia score multiple dispatch
is uh this is a quote from Wikipedia and
you know in uh in more layman's terms
it's u this this uh property where you
can have the the same function you're
using the same name having different uh
methods implemented for it and by
methods we mean uh the combinations of
its arguments can be different. Uh some
some methods can have more or less
arguments than others or some methods
can have exactly the same number of
arguments as others just with different
types. Right? So you can see uh the
definition of an F function having two
methods. Right? The first method works
with only uh floatingoint neurons of
sorry floatingoint numbers with 64-bit
precision. And then we define a second
method that works with any number.
number is a is a is an abstract uh type
you know over floating uh floats. So as
you can see when we call f using a float
2.0 and an integer three then the second
method gets gets evaluated right because
that's that's that's the best match that
we have. But if we call f with a 2.0 and
a 3.0 zero then the first one gets u
gets called right because both of those
numbers are floats and they're they're
float 64 by default uh in Julia and uh
you can see proof of that at the end uh
that that symbol between float and
number that bins subtype so this is just
a logical uh comparator of types if you
want to that uh you compare float to
number and you get true because you're
claiming that float is a super sorry
float is a subtype of a of a number. Um
so that's why those evaluations work.
And now types float 64s and numbers
those are Julia types but also you can
define your own types and we will do
that tomorrow when we define our own
blockes. And on the on the right here
you see you can see an example of u
defining structure called my type.
Structures are any are collections of
elements. They're like composite
composite data types. uh and within your
structure you can uh you can explicitly
you know cast the type on on any of the
of the of the of the variables that the
type holds or you can just leave it
blank and it can take any type of input.
For instance, here in my type, X has no
type, right? So X can be any type in
Julia. Y is strictly an integer and Z is
a float 64, right? So we can see that my
type when the first thing is is a string
called yellow uh perfectly
works. And the combination of these two
uh concepts, you know, custom types with
multiple dispatch can extend uh Julia's
features
by by basically unpredictable amounts.
You can do u so many things and you know
borrowing this term from complex systems
we can see the we can see emergent
features in the language and you you
will see an example of that and by
emerging features I mean we can uh take
types and functions that are not
designed to work together but they just
work together maybe by defining one more
method or maybe doing like sometimes
with with adding no extra code but
sometimes with minimal extra code. So we
see this unpredictable behavior coming
here and there that are you know welcome
features to have
u now on performance this is the runs
like c uh parts of that famous mantra u
here I'm just showing you some benchmark
uh with popular functions some of them
come from uh linear algebra like some
matrix multiplication or matrix
statistics uh some of them are just
recursions like the there's a recursive
calculator of the Fibonacci sequence and
as you can See on the on the x- axis
here we have different languages and
they're all compared to C. That's why C
is collapsed in one point and as you can
see Julia is very much approximating uh
C behavior in most of those benchmarks
and you can see this in stark contrast
with other high level languages uh like
MATLAB are
um uh
octave. Now I also want to make a
comment about the Julia community. Uh
discourse.julang.org is a is a forum
dedicated to the Julia language and it's
uh it's highly active and you can get an
answer on any question that you have
there and if it's not there it's going
to be on the Julia Slack. Uh that's the
general general Julia Slack that you can
uh join for free. There is a there's a
link through the Julia web page. Um but
even these are some statistics from the
uh user survey. Uh and you can see that
you know the ever
since Julia 1 1.0 zero which is the
beginning of the x-axis that's 2018.
You can see how the the forum has been
the community has been growing both of
you know active users and also of the
page
views. Um and also in terms of u you
know learning components if you want to
explore Julia more this also comes from
the developer survey 2023 where you know
the survey was asking participants what
resources that have you found most
useful when learning Julia for the first
time or were when learning to do
something new in Julia. So most people
um answered that they they use the Julia
manual and I I add this slide here
because I know that sometimes the the
you know the official manual can can uh
put people off. I think it's not always
welld designigned in every language or
you know any any software but in Julia
this is very much the case. I think the
the Julia manual it manual itself it's
very useful. So I would urge you if you
want to look more into Julia to
definitely look into the manual but also
on the other main categories for
instance Julia con presentations and
YouTube tutorials and Julia books we
have references that fall into these
categories in the introduction to Julia
page and you will see that on the the
website. Um so yeah if you want to learn
more about Julia you'll have plenty of
resources and also feel free to ask us
both today and any other day uh during
the
workshop and uh yeah I think yeah this
is my last slide for now. So do have any
questions on the introduction to
Julia? No. Okay cool. So we can start
with uh the actual exercises. So you can
navigate
to the introduction to Julia
page. Uh you can do this both from the
side menu by the way but also from the
homepage when you have all the units and
the first notebook is the Julia intro.
Um where basically when you start
running uh Jupiter for the first time,
you will get a window like this, right?
So you need to navigate uh to the folder
where all the notebooks are and open
Julro and you will do the same with any
future notebook. Uh just one comment on
uh the Jul intro uh this first notebook
is that this is quite lengthy but it has
a lot of useful material but I would say
in the in the interest of time uh I
would urge you to skip the the
performance
session which is
So it
open. Yeah. from uh here towards the end
you will see after the types stability
definitely go through that
um but uh yeah actually sorry not sorry
that's my
bad so yeah after this uh the section on
functions that is here on cells you know
around 100 180. Uh you can stop and
switch to the to the second notebook.
And because this last bit of the of the
notebook is about uh performance and how
Julia manages to be so performant and
what you can do in your Julia code to
make it run faster. So I left it in uh
but in the interest of time uh we can
skip it for now and move on to the
second notebook. And you can always come
back if you're interested in performance
or how Julia does it. We can come back
and do this last
section.
Yeah. So, yeah, feel free to start with
the notebooks and ask any questions
either on Slack or raise your hand and
we'll be around to answer them.